Welcome to today's deep dive. I want you to to visualize a document for a second. I'm a document. Yeah, like a job description for a board member
Oh, right. Maybe it's for a massive fortune 500 company or or just you know, the local nonprofit down the street
Exactly, and you know exactly what's on that paper. It's a list of very dry
very serious bullet points
fiduciary oversight
governance
Strategic planning adherence to bylaws, right adherence to bylaws. It smells like like stale coffee and legal pads
It's the standard operating procedure
I mean, it's what the lawyers tell you to write down so you don't get sued basically, right?
But we have a stack of sources today that we're diving into
Centered around the work of Jim Morgan and also this really interesting case study from the positive coaching alliance
Yeah, the PCA and these sources suggest that that piece of paper is missing the single most important requirement
Morgan's stance on this is it's pretty provocative
It really is he argues that you can follow every rule on that list perfectly like you can check every single fiduciary box and
Still absolutely destroy the organization, right? Because essentially he's saying that the job description is a bit of a red herring
Yeah, the real job isn't about policy. It's about behavior. It's not what you vote on it's
It's how you act in the hallway and that's exactly what our mission is for this deep dive today
We are exploring this concept called tone at the top tone of the top right now
Usually when I hear corporate culture, I kind of roll my eyes a little bit
Oh, I think of you know HR initiatives or mandatory fun days or there's motivational posters in the break room
Yes, the ones about synergy with the rowers
But the argument here is that culture isn't a program you run. It's a physics problem
It flows downhill and it closed from a very specific source
We aren't just talking about the CEO or the executive director here
We are talking about the board of directors the people who might only meet what four times a year exactly and
Morgan's central thesis and this is the part that might make some listeners a little uncomfortable
Is that the way those people treat each other inside a closed room?
Dictates how the receptionist treats a client six months later see and that's where I get stuck
That feels like a massive leap to me. Does the receptionist or the mid-level manager really care what the board does?
Well, they might not consciously care right because they might never even meet these people
How does the behavior of a board member?
Infect the daily culture of the office if they aren't even in the building most of the time
That is exactly the question we need to answer today because the mechanism is invisible
But it is incredibly potent and to understand it. We're gonna look at two very different worlds
The boardroom in the basketball court, right?
We've got the high stakes world of corporate governance
And then we have this sort of lab experiment that I think makes this much clear
Which is the sidelines of youth sports, which I honestly didn't expect to see in a business research packet
But you're saying a little league dugout has the exact same political structure as a corporate boardroom
It really does the dynamics of authority in emulation and those unwritten rules. They're identical
If we can understand why a dad screaming at a referee ruins a soccer team
We can understand why a board member checking their email ruins a non-profit. All right
Well, let's get into the mechanism first tone at the top. It sounds like a buzzword. What does Jim Morgan actually mean by this?
So Morgan strips away the jargon entirely he defines tone at the top specifically regarding boards as the
interpersonal culture of the board itself not by a loss, right is not about the strategic plan
They write it is about how they treat one another while they are running it
He argues that the board doesn't just supervise the organization. The board is the organization's nervous system
But typically the board is seen as a separate entity, right? They are the oversight the staff does the actual work
Why isn't there a firewall there because humans are social animals and we are wired for survival in
Any hierarchy the people at the bottom are constantly scanning the people at the top for cues like how do I survive here?
Exactly. What is rewarded? What is punished?
Morgan explains that behavior flows downhill because staff emulate their superiors to stay safe. So it's not just mimicry
It's signaling exactly. It's profound signaling
If the board members are courteous and respectful and genuinely engaged with one another the senior management sees that they say
Okay to succeed here. I need to be collaborative
So they emulate it and then middle management emulate senior management, right?
but the inverse is where it gets incredibly dangerous if the board is dysfunctional if they are snippy with each other or if they roll
Their eyes when someone speaks or if they are dismissive of the executive director that toxicity flows right down to the intern
You mentioned rolling eyes or checking phones. That seems so minor though. Does that really move the needle on a whole culture?
It's a massive signal actually. It signals what you are saying doesn't matter
And once that signal is sent from the top
You cannot stop it from reaching the bottom. Wow. Morgan is very clear on this
No amount of staff retreats or sensitivity training or culture initiatives will fix a toxicity that is originating from the board
You can't clean the river if someone is dumping sludge at the source
So let's look at what this dysfunction actually looks like in practice
Because I assume most board members think they're doing a good job
They aren't waking up thinking I'm gonna go be toxic today rare is the villain who thinks they're the villain Morgan identifies two main modes of failure for struggling boards
They are opposites, but they're equally damaging. Let's hear them. The first is the micromanager
Oh, the helicopter parent of the boardroom. Exactly. This is the board that just doesn't trust the staff
They pick apart every single line item on the budget. They red line press releases
They debate the color of the napkins at the annual gala and the message that sends to the staff is pretty clear
You are incompetent or we don't trust you and think about the result of that if I don't trust you
You stop taking risks. You stop being creative
You just try to avoid getting yelled at and so the organization stagnates. Okay, so that's one extreme
What's the other failure mode? The second one is actually more common in the nonprofit world and it's arguably
More insidious. It's the rubber stamp the just sign it and let's go home approach precisely
This is the board that engages in zero debate
Yeah, they skim the packet five minutes before the meeting or honestly, maybe they don't read it at all right
They're just physically present barely they nod their heads
They prove the motion and they check their watches because they have a tea time or a dinner reservation on the surface though
Wouldn't a staff actually prefer that you get your approval? You don't get micromanaged and you move on it sounds easier short term
Yes, it's easier long term. It's fatal because the message the rubber stamp board sends is we don't care
And if the top authority doesn't care, why should the staff?
Why should the development director stay late to finish that grant application if the board won't even read it?
It breeds a culture of deep apathy. So between the micromanaging and the neglect you have this mirror effect
That's the key phrase in the research
Leaders need to understand that how they show up in the room echoes through every hallway
Morgan emphasizes that this isn't about being inspirational
We tend to overvalue charisma in leadership. We want the big speech from Braveheart. We do we want the Steve Jobs reality distortion field
But Morgan says forget inspirational. Just be intentional be curious ask hard questions, but do it respectfully
Disagree without being disagreeable because everyone is watching it's about the subtle signals of respect
Okay, so that's the boardroom theory
But the sources take this high-level corporate concept and drop it into a context that feels a lot more visceral
We're moving from the boardroom to the basketball court now. Yes, the positive coaching alliance or PCA
Think of this as our living lab for these theories. They've been testing this in the real world since 1998
And honestly the stakes feel most clearer here if a board is dysfunctional
You lose money or efficiency if a youth sports environment is toxic
You're actually damaging kids. That's totally fair and the PCA framework is basically Jim Morgan's philosophy
But with a whistle and a clipboard
Their premise is that in youth sports the adults the coaches the parents the league admins
They set the tone for the child's experience
The rulebook is irrelevant if the humans are flawed precise
They have a specific term for the ideal leader here to the double goal coach
Break that down for us because usually a coach just has one goal, which is win the game, right?
So goal one is winning they aren't naive
I know scoreboards exist and competition is healthy. They aren't saying winning doesn't matter, right?
But goal two which they argue must be superior to
Goal one is teaching life lessons through sports
Now that sounds like a really nice poster to hang in the locker room
But in the heat of a game when you're down by two points with a minute left those two goals are gonna collide constantly and
That collision is where the culture is actually formed. That's the moment of truth
Let's look at the behavioral echoes
Imagine a close game a referee makes a terrible call against your team just blatantly wrong the coach has two choices
Choice a the coach screams at the referee throws their hat kicks the dirt and turns purple
Which I have seen happen a hundred times. I've probably seen it this month. We all have now forget the referee for a second
What is the lesson that flows downhill to the players watching that coach?
The lesson is the system is rate authority is the enemy and the way to handle adversity is to throw a tantrum exactly
You are teaching players that lack of control is an acceptable response to pressure
You're teaching them that the external world is always to blame for their problems, but look at choice beat. Okay, the coach gets the bad call
They are angry because they're human, but they respond with composure. They ask for clarification calmly
They turn back to the huddle and say bad call play on
Focus on the next play that teaches resilience
It teaches that you can control your reaction even when you can't control the outcome and that lesson sticks way longer than the score
The game that is tone at the top translated to the sideline
But the source material points out that this ecosystem is even larger than the coach
It's not just one person the coach has a boss to it's a hierarchy just like the corporation
The league administrator sets the tone for the coaches
If the league director is disorganized or cuts corners on safety checks or plays favorites with scheduling
The coaches feel permitted to do the exact same thing
Then the coaches set the tone for the players and then you have the third rail
The parents the parents in the stands
This is where the culture usually falls apart in my experience it is and think about the flow downhill concept again
If a parent is screaming at the umpire from the bleachers
They are actively undermining the coach's attempt to teach respect
They are creating a counterculture right there in the stands
There's a visual from the source that really stuck with me regarding this disconnect
They talk about wallpaper and this is where it really clicks for me. I love this analogy. It's haunting actually
The idea is that you can have the best youth sports policy in the world
You can have a shiny handbook that says we value
Sportsmanship and respect
But if the head coach is angry and the director is cutting corners that policy is just wallpaper. It's decoration
It covers the cracks in the wall, but doesn't hold the house up. In fact, it's worse than that
It creates an illusion of structural integrity
You think you have a values-based organization because it's written on the wall, but the foundation is rotting
That applies to so many things beyond sports to corporate value statements wallpaper
Family rules that the parents don't follow wall paper
It's the difference between what is declared and what is performed culture is performed
If your values are only on paper, you don't actually have values. You just have marketing now
We're treating this like a discovery of modern organizational psychology
But looking at the broader historical context in the notes, this isn't exactly new
We are effectively rediscovering something that was obvious to people 2000 years ago. We really are if we zoom out Jim Morgan
Isn't just quoting business theory. He's channeling ancient political philosophy. He's just wearing a suit instead of a toga
You're referencing the Play-Doh connection here
I am in the Republic Play-Doh spent a lot of time arguing that the character of a state's leaders
Directly shapes the moral fabric of society. He didn't talk about skills or efficiency or q3 earnings
He talked about virtue. He argued for philosopher kings who embodied prudence and justice not just because it's nice to be nice though
No strictly practical he believed the conduct of the leader was inseparable from the health of the society if the leader is corrupt
The society inevitable becomes corrupt. It's a contagion and Aristotle backed this up, too, right?
He did in his ethics. He asserted that the ethical conduct of those in power permeates everything beneath it
So when Morgan talks about a board member needing to show respect to a colleague during a budget dispute
He's basically proving Aristotle, right?
There is a quote from Ralph Waldo Emerson in the notes that I think captures this better than any business textbook
What you are speak so loudly. I can't hear what you're saying. It's
Devastatingly accurate think about that in the context of the rubber stamp board member. We talked about earlier. They might be saying
We are committed to this non-profit submission
But if they show up unprepared and check their emails their behavior is screaming, I don't care and that screen drowns out the mission statement
And we should note this isn't just philosophy either. We have modern data on this the notes reference Edgar shines research at MIT
Wait, he's the organizational culture guy. He found that an organization's behavior is shaped by deeply held assumptions
That's academic speak for how leaders act when things get real
It's easy to have good values when profits are up or when the team is winning by 20 points
Anyone can be a double-goal coach when they're winning exactly
The board's real values aren't in the strategic plan
They're revealed in how they treat each other when they disagree on a budget cut the coach's real values aren't in the pregame speech
They're revealed when the team is down by 10 points with two minutes left and the ref is blowing calls
That is the moment the culture is set speaking of sports and values
the source brings up Tony Dungey and I think he is the perfect
Counter-argument to the idea that you have to be a loud aggressive
Alpha leader to set a strong tone because we usually think tone at the top means volume at the top absolutely
Tony Dungey was the first African-American head coach to win a Super Bowl and if you watch him on the sidelines
His style was famously quiet. He didn't scream. He didn't rule through fear. He didn't throw headsets
He built his teams on consistency character and accountability. He proved that tone doesn't mean volume. That's the key distinction
Tone is not volume. It's values made visible
Dungey expected his players to follow his lead and because his lead was so steady they did
He didn't just win games. He built a culture that survived even when he left the room. So we've established the mechanism here
We have the philosophy the data the sports analogies
But looking at the current landscape described in the sources, we seem to be in a bit of a crisis
This isn't just theoretical organizations are hurting
They are in the nonprofit world the data shows boards are struggling significantly
You have members who show up quarterly skim the financials nod through the agenda and feel like they've done their duty
Meanwhile executive directors are burning out at record rates because they are managing up
Right, they're spending all their energy trying to keep the board happy or engaged
Instead of leading the organization and the staff sees this they see the gap between the stated values of the mission
And the disengagement of leadership that gap is where cynicism is born and in youth sports
It's the exact same gap
Leagues print beautiful handbooks about respect and then the first tense game happens the parents go wild and the handbook is ignored
It's the wallpaper effect in action
Everyone knows the values are fake and that breeds profound cynicism. Okay, so let's get practical here for a minute
If you are listening to this whether you are a ceo a board member
A soccer coach or just a parent
How do you fix the wallpaper? How do you make the culture real? Because
Be virtuous like play-doh is a pretty tall order for a Tuesday morning
The sources give us a really specific actionable tip. They do and I love how deceptively simple this is
It's called the 10 minute rule walk us through it. The advice is arrive 10 minutes early
Whether it's a board meeting a shift at work or a soccer practice
And in those 10 minutes your only job is to have one genuine
Non-agenda conversation just talk to someone that's the fix that sounds almost too easy
It sounds too small doesn't it but think about the intent if you're a board member you find a staff member
Maybe someone you usually ignore if you're a coach you find a player who had a rough week
Yes, how are you or how was school and you actually listen to the answer?
Why does that change the culture? It shifts the dynamic from transactional to relational
It establishes a human connection before the business begins
PCA teaches coaches that the first five minutes of practice set the tone for the whole session
If you start with connection the rest follows if you start with chaos or detachment
You're fighting uphill for the next hour. It forces the leader to be present. You can't fake that. Yes
You can't have a genuine conversation if you're checking your email or thinking about your next meeting
It forces you to model the engagement you want to see it signals
I am here and I see you it's a small investment just 10 minutes
But it builds incredible social capital and notice it doesn't cost any money
You don't need a consultant for this. You don't need a budget approval. You just need to show up and be a human being
It turns the tone at the top from a concept into an action as we wrap this up
Let's circle back to that job description
We started with the one with the bullet points about governance and duties the one that completely misses the point
We've effectively rewritten the job description for anyone in charge of anything today
The sources are uncompromising on this. There is no firewall. No firewall. You cannot separate who you are from how you lead
The board's culture is the nonprofit's culture
The coach's behavior is the team's identity
You can't outsource culture to a committee or a document
It's a sobering thought whether you are running a fortune 500 company or just running a car pool
You are setting a tone
You are creating a microculture in that car or that boardroom and the question isn't are you setting a tone?
You are whether you like it or not. The question is
Is it the tone you want?
Intentionality is the only difference between a toxic culture and a thriving one. Well, this has been a fantastic look at the invisible forces that shape
Our organizations
I'm definitely going to be thinking about that wallpaper analogy the next time I see a mission statement on a wall
It's a hard image to shake once you see it before we go
I want to leave everyone with that final provocative thought from our source material
We talked about emerson saying what you are speak so loudly. I can't hear what you're saying
It brings it all back to behavior. So the question for you to mull over today is this
If you stop talking right now
What are you still saying to the people around you just by being you?
That's the question. Thanks for diving in with us. We'll see you next time