Culture eats strategy for breakfast.
Yeah.
You have heard it, I have heard it.
It's probably plastered on a poster
in your break room right now,
maybe peeling a little at the corners.
And honestly, I kind of hate that phrase.
You hate it.
That's a pretty strong reaction to a business classic.
I do.
It just feels like one of those things consultants say
when they don't really have a real answer.
Right.
It is catchy, sure, but what does it actually mean?
It feels like a cliche that just gets thrown around
in boardrooms to sort of shut down the conversation.
It is basically the live laugh love of the corporate world.
Okay, that is a fair critique.
It has absolutely become a bumper sticker,
but here's the thing about cliches,
and I really hate to be the one to defend them,
but usually they become cliches
because there is a massive fundamental truth
buried in there somewhere.
We just stop hearing it
because we have heard it way too often.
Okay, so you were saying
there is actually some meat on the bone here.
There is a lot of meat,
and that is exactly what we are doing today
in this deep dive.
We are dusting off that phrase
and looking at what it actually means,
not as a slogan, but as a literal survival mechanism.
Right, and before we really get into the how of all this,
I need to wrap my head around our source material for today.
Sure.
Because we are looking at insights from Jim Morgan
who led applied materials.
That's a massive high tech company.
Right, a global tech giant.
Exactly, but this analysis is being presented
in a co-branded deep dive with Kalan Profits,
the California Association of Non-profits.
That just seems like a really odd couple to me.
It does sound like a total mismatch, doesn't it?
Yeah.
I have this Titan of Silicon Valley,
a guy who ran a hardware empire for nearly three decades,
and then you have the nonprofit sector.
But the reason they are paired up
is really the core of our discussion today.
Which is what exactly?
That human behavior doesn't change
just because your tax status does.
Oh, wow, okay.
Morgan's entire argument is that organizations,
whether they are manufacturing microchips
or feeding the unhoused,
they all fall into the exact same traps
when things get tough.
Okay, let's talk about those traps then.
Because usually when an organization is struggling,
right, sales are down, or maybe donors are ghosting you,
morale is just in the toilet.
Leadership loves to pivot to strategy.
Oh, we are completely addicted to strategy.
It feels safe, it feels intellectual and rigorous.
You hire a consultant,
you draft this massive five-year plan,
maybe you reorganize the whole org chart,
it feels like you are doing something productive.
But Morgan is saying that is the wrong move.
He says it is effectively useless
if your culture is broken.
Useless.
Completely.
He argues that if the underlying system
of how people actually interact with each other is flawed,
no amount of brilliant strategy is gonna save you.
You can have the best map in the world,
but if your car has no engine, you aren't going anywhere.
So the mission for today's deep dive
is to explain why culture isn't just a vibe.
I feel like we use that word way too much,
like, oh, the culture's a bad vibe.
Yeah, way too much.
We want to look at it as a system of deliberate actions.
And specifically, we are going to see how this applies
to the nonprofit sector in California,
where the stakes for you and your communities
are honestly terrifyingly high.
They are incredibly high.
And I think we need to start by dismantling the thing
most companies do instead of actually fixing their culture.
The ritual.
Yes, the offsite ritual.
Oh, man, I know this ritual.
I have lived this ritual so many times.
Walk me through it.
What does it look like?
Okay, so the numbers are bad.
Yeah.
Everyone is completely stressed out.
The CEO stands up and says, we have a culture problem.
So what do they do?
They book a hotel.
Exactly.
They book a hotel conference room
with those terrible humming, fluorescent lights.
They order some stale pastries.
And they hold the offsite.
The dreaded two-day offsite.
Yes.
You spend two whole days doing trust falls
or putting sticky notes on a whiteboard.
You come up with big buzzwords like synergy
and excellence and innovation.
And everyone feels really good for about,
I don't know, six hours.
It is like a sugar rush.
And then what happens?
Then you go back to the office on Monday morning.
You open your laptop.
The huge pile of work is still sitting right there.
The annoying coworker is still just as annoying.
And by Tuesday at lunch,
that new culture is completely dead.
Exactly.
Morgan has seen this exact scenario a thousand times.
He says the reason the offsite fails
is that it treats culture as an event.
An event.
Yeah.
You cannot change an organization's character
just by telling people it needs to change for 48 hours.
It feels like trying to get in shape
by reading a book about jogging
while you're eating a donut.
That is a perfect analogy.
The offsite is the book about jogging.
It might help you diagnose that you are out of shape.
Sure, it might even get everyone in the room
to agree that jogging is a good idea.
But it is not the run itself.
Morgan's entire philosophy pivots
on this idea of deliberate action.
Deliberate action.
That sounds a lot less fluffy
than trust falls and sticky notes.
It is basically engineering.
Morgan insists that culture is built through structure,
processes, and people.
It is reinforced day after day
in all the boring mundane stuff.
It is not a feeling, it is the operating system.
Oh, I like that.
The offsite is just a screensaver.
It looks pretty, it bounces around,
but it doesn't do any of the actual processing work.
That distinction is great.
Operating system versus screensaver.
But let me push back a little bit here.
It is really easy for a billionaire tech CEO
to talk about deliberate action and structure.
True.
He has infinite resources.
He has armies of people to implement these things.
We are applying this to the nonprofit sector.
Does this actually translate to a small organization
that is just screaching by on grants?
That is the million dollar question right there.
Or actually looking at the data,
it's the 200 billion dollar question.
Wait, 200 billion?
Let's look at the actual data from count nonprofits.
They released a research report called Causes Count.
And I think most people,
when they hear the word nonprofit,
they picture a local soup kitchen or a tiny charity.
They just think small.
Right, just nice people doing nice things
on a shoestring budget.
But the reality is that the nonprofit sector in California
employs over 1.2 million people.
Whoa, 1.2 million.
Yeah, let's put that number in perspective for you.
That is bigger than the entire construction industry
in California.
You're kidding.
No, it is bigger than the finance and insurance sectors too.
It generates over $200 billion in revenue.
So if the nonprofit sector has a culture crisis,
it is not just a charity problem.
It is a massive economic liability for the entire state.
That completely changes the gravity of the conversation.
We aren't just talking about making volunteers
feel fuzzy and appreciated.
We are talking about the efficiency
of a huge chunk of the economy.
Exactly, we are talking about the engine
that holds the entire social safety net together.
And right now it's running on broken pistons.
And the source material highlights
that this engine is running incredibly hot.
Because they're under resourced.
Right, these organizations are often under staff,
underfunded, and they are dealing with some
of the most difficult, heartbreaking,
societal problems imaginable.
Which creates a very specific, intense kind of burnout,
doesn't it?
Because in the corporate world,
if you burn out and drop the ball,
maybe you lose a quarterly bonus.
But in the nonprofit world, if you burn out,
maybe a vulnerable community doesn't get fed that week.
The guilt factor alone must be huge.
It is immense, the pressure is constant.
And that leads directly to the trap we mentioned earlier
with the strategy obsession.
When you are that overwhelmed
and you are running on fumes,
your human instinct is to do something to fix it.
Right.
So you launch a brand new initiative.
You write a new glossy strategic plan
to show your donors that you are innovating.
Because you always have to show impact
to get the next grant.
Exactly.
But Morgan points out that adding a new strategic plan
on top of a broken, burnt out culture
is like building a second story on a house
that has a crumbling foundation.
It's just gonna collapse faster.
Exactly.
The weight of the new strategy
just crushes whatever morale is left.
So the solution isn't a flashier fundraising gala
or a better brochure.
No.
The solution is to treat your culture
as a core organizational asset.
An asset just like your office building
or your donor database or your endowment.
Right.
The organizations that actually thrive,
the ones that retain their staff
and keep donors coming back year after year
are the ones that ruthlessly prioritize
the internal way they work together.
There is this concept of the ripple effect
mentioned in the source material.
And since we're talking about 10,000 member organizations
and counting profits,
that ripple could really be a tidal wave.
Think about the sheer scale of it.
If just a fraction of those 10,000 organizations
improve their culture, even just incrementally,
you get what Morgan calls compound interest on culture.
Compound interest on culture.
I love that.
Because less burnout means lower turnover.
And turnover is so incredibly expensive.
It is devastating to a budget.
Think about the recruitment costs, the training time,
the lost institutional knowledge.
If you fix the culture, you keep the people.
If you keep the people, you keep the expertise.
Which means more money and time
actually goes directly to the mission.
Yes.
So paradoxically, stopping to fix your internal feelings
and workflows is actually the most efficient,
hard-nosed financial decision a leader can make.
Okay.
I am totally sold on the why here.
Fixing culture is an efficiency strategy,
plain and simple.
But let's get into the how for the listeners.
Because deliberate action still feels
just a little vague to me.
If I am a leader listening to this right now,
what am I actually supposed to do
on a random Tuesday morning?
Like, does this start with HR at the CEO's job?
This is where it gets really interesting
and honestly, maybe a little uncomfortable
for some of the people listening.
Morgan is absolutely adamant about this.
Culture starts at the board level.
The board.
Really?
That feels so distant from the day to day.
I know it does.
Usually the board shows up, you know,
once a quarter of the educated sandwich,
they look at a spreadsheet and then they leave.
How on earth do they impact the daily culture
of the frontline staff?
Morgan calls it tone at the top.
And he isn't talking about their fun reason connections
or their wealth, he is talking strictly
about their behavior in those meetings.
Give me a specific example.
What does that look like?
Okay, imagine a quarterly board meeting.
The executive director is presenting
a really critical report.
One of the board members is just staring down,
checking their email on their phone the whole time.
Another one interrupts the director mid-sentence
to ask a question that was already answered
on page one of the packet.
Okay, I am physically cringing right now
because I have seen that exact scenario happen.
We all have.
Now, what does that behavior actually signal to the room?
It signals that listening isn't important.
It signals that hierarchy matters more than basic respect.
It signals that we don't really care what you have to say.
Wow.
And that energy flows downhill.
Like gravity.
It is exactly like gravity.
If the board treats the CEO with disrespect,
the CEO is going to leave that meeting stressed out.
They are more likely to be short with their VPs.
The VPs take that stress out on the managers
and eventually the frontline staff is absolutely miserable.
That makes total sense.
You cannot have a toxic board
and expect a healthy staff culture.
It just doesn't work.
That is a pretty heavy realization
because it means no amount of staff, pizza parties
or employee of the month awards can fix a rot
that is coming from the very top of the org chart.
Precisely.
You cannot train your way
out of a leadership modeling problem.
But, and this is a really big but,
Morgan also insists that while it starts at the top,
it absolutely does not stay there.
What do you mean by that?
He talks about this idea of collective ownership.
He says it is every single team member's job
to walk the talk.
Okay.
It isn't a special project for the HR department
to just roll out and memo.
Culture is what happens
in every single interaction between colleagues.
So it's not just the board member checking their email.
It's, you know, how I respond to you
when you make a mistake on a project.
Exactly.
Do I shame you in front of the team?
Do I ignore it and fix it myself aggressively?
Or do I pull you aside
and help you figure out what went wrong?
Right.
Micro interaction, that right there is the culture.
It is the aggregate of a thousand tiny decisions
made by everyone every single day.
You know, as we are talking about all of this,
Morgan's advice, the structure, the discipline of it all,
it sounds very modern.
Yeah.
It sounds like something you would hear
at a slick TED talk in San Francisco.
But reading through the deep dive materials,
what really struck me is that none of this is actually new.
Oh no, it is not new at all.
In fact, the commentary suggests
that Morgan is basically just channeling
some very old ghosts here.
Absolutely.
And this is honestly one of my favorite parts
of this entire analysis.
Morgan sounds like a modern tech CEO,
but he is essentially preaching ancient philosophy.
I really want to dig into this
because it feels like a bit of a stretch at first glance.
How do we get from a Silicon Valley executive to,
well, I assume we are going to ancient Greece.
We are definitely going to ancient Greece.
Plato and Aristotle specifically.
Okay, connect those dots for me.
How does Plato fit into corporate culture?
Let's look at Plato's Republic.
We are talking over 2,400 years ago.
Plato argued that the character
and the virtues of a state's leaders
shape the entire society's moral fabric.
Which is exactly the tone at the top concept.
It is almost verbatim.
Plato was basically saying,
you cannot legislate greatness.
You cannot write a law that simply forces people to be good.
Just like Morgan says,
you can't just send out a memo to create a good culture.
The leader's virtue sets the ceiling
for the entire organization.
If the leader is corrupt or lazy, the state is corrupt.
Okay, so Plato gives us the leadership modeling angles.
What about the deliberate action part?
Where does that come in?
That is all Aristotle.
In Nicomachean ethics, Aristotle argues
that virtue is not a state of being, it is a habit.
A habit?
Yes, he has this incredibly famous idea
that we are what we repeatedly do.
We are what we repeatedly do.
You know, that sounds like a poster too.
It does, but think about the actual mechanics
of what he is saying.
Aristotle would have absolutely hated the corporate offside.
Oh, he would have stormed out of the conference room.
He would have.
He would have said,
you don't become brave by going to a two day seminar
on the theory of bravery.
You become brave by actually doing brave things
repeatedly until it's natural.
Right, you don't become a master pianist
just by watching a concert.
You have to do the scales every day.
Exactly.
And Morgan is saying the exact same thing to leaders today.
You become a transparent, respectful organization
by actually practicing transparency and respect
every single day until it becomes a reflex.
That makes so much sense.
It takes the concept out of the realm of corporate speak
and puts it right into the realm of basic human nature.
I love that framing.
It really validates the idea
that this isn't just some passing business fad.
It is literally how humans are wired to operate.
But the source material also bridges this ancient wisdom
to something a bit more modern and relatable than Aristotle.
Yes.
Sports legends.
Yeah, and I think this is where the discipline aspect
really shines through because sometimes
when we talk about culture, it still sounds a bit soft.
But then you look at someone like Pat Summit.
The legendary Tennessee women's basketball coach.
Right, the winningest coach in division I history
at the time she retired.
She did not build that absolute powerhouse
of a program on vibes or just holding hands.
Definitely not.
She's invested on explicit, rigorous standards
of accountability.
She has this incredible quote that I think sums it all up.
Culture isn't inspiration.
It's infrastructure.
Culture is infrastructure.
I want to pause on that word for a second
because infrastructure feels really cold.
It feels like concrete and rebar and bridges.
It doesn't feel like a people focused word.
But that is exactly why it is so brilliant.
Think about it.
Infrastructure supports everything else you want to do.
If the bridge is out, it doesn't matter how fast
or nice your car is, you are not crossing the river.
That's true.
Summit meant that you build standards, how we practice,
how we treat each other in the locker room,
how we study film, and those standards,
that infrastructure holds the weight of the team
when things get really hard.
So when the pressure's on in the fourth quarter
of a championship game, you don't magically rise
to the occasion, you just fall back
to the level of your training.
Exactly, you fall to the level of your infrastructure.
And John Wooden is mentioned in there too, right?
The famous pyramid of success.
Yeah, you really can't talk about team culture
without bringing up Wooden.
His whole philosophy was about losing yourself
for the good of the group.
Which connects perfectly back to Morgan's point
about collective ownership.
Exactly, it is not about you being a superstar player.
It is about the team functioning seamlessly
as a single unit.
And just to bring this all the way back
to the nonprofit world for our listeners,
the source also mentions Francis Husslebeam.
Oh, she is an absolute giant in the nonprofit field,
former CEO of the Girl Scouts.
She argued that values are not just nice ideas,
they are operational standards.
Okay, operational standards sounds a bit jargonetomy.
Can we unpack what that actually means on the ground?
Sure, think of it like the speed limit on a highway.
The employee handbook, which is your strategy,
might say the speed limit is 55 miles per hour.
But let's say the CEO drives past you
every single morning doing 90,
and nobody ever gets a ticket.
What is the actual speed limit on that road?
Well, it's 90.
Exactly, the behavior completely overrides the rulebook.
That behavior is the operational standard.
Husslebeam, Morgan, Plato, Pat, Summit,
they are all saying the exact same thing across centuries.
Which is?
If you say you value work-life balance in your strategy,
but your operational standard is that you email your staff
at 11.00 PM on a Saturday and demand an immediate answer,
the 11.00 PM email wins every single time.
That is the culture eats strategy moment right there,
isn't it?
It is.
Your strategy says retain our valuable staff,
but your operational standard says
burn them out on the weekends.
Culture wins, the staff leaves, the strategy fails.
Every single time, you simply cannot fool the room.
People will always believe what they see you do,
not what they hear you say.
All right, so we have established the problem,
which is the offsite trap and the reliance on strategy.
We have established the stakes,
looking at the massive economic engine
of the nonprofit sector,
and we have connected it to the deep history
of how humans have always organized themselves.
But as we wrap up, I wanna leave the listener
with something they can actually do today.
Yes, because if we just sit here
and talk about it abstractly,
we are falling into the exact same trap
we just spent 20 minutes criticizing.
We are just having a podcast offsite.
Exactly, I don't wanna just talk about jogging.
I want everyone to put on their shoes.
Yeah.
So Morgan has a very specific challenge
for you, the listener,
and I have to be completely honest.
When I read this in the deep dive,
my stomach dropped a little bit.
It is intimidating.
It sounds so simple,
but it sounds genuinely scary for a leader to actually do.
It is terrifying if you do it right,
but it is really the only way
to get an honest baseline of your current infrastructure.
Okay, so here is the exercise for you.
Sometime this week,
find three people in your organization,
but, and this is the crucial part,
do not ask your direct reports.
Right, because if you ask the people
whose performance reviews you write,
they are gonna tell you exactly what you wanna hear.
Right, self-preservation.
You need to go deeper,
go a level or two down the work chart,
or ask people in a completely different department.
You have to get out of your immediate echo chamber.
Okay, so you find these three people
and you ask them one simple question, ready?
The question is,
what is one thing about how we work together
that we say we value,
but we don't actually do?
Yeah, that right there is the seto gap.
And here is the rule,
which I think is definitely the hardest part
of the whole exercise.
You have to just listen.
You cannot defend yourself.
You cannot explain away their answer.
That is the killer.
The urge to explain is so strong.
Oh, it really is.
If they look at you and say,
well, we say we value transparency,
but all the real decisions are made behind closed doors.
You cannot say, well, actually,
that was because of specific legal issue.
You just have to nod and say, thank you for telling me.
And that uncomfortable silence?
That is where the actual learning happens,
because whatever they tell you,
that specific gap between the shiny poster on the wall
and the messy reality on the ground,
that is where your culture actually lives.
Wow.
That gap is your culture.
It is a massive reality check.
And I can completely see why leaders avoid doing this.
Who wants to voluntarily hear
that they aren't living up to their own stated values?
Nobody wants to hear that.
It hurts your ego.
But for the Count and Profits members listening to this,
or really anyone leading a team,
imagine if every leader did that this week.
The ripple effect.
Exactly.
Imagine the uncomfortable,
but entirely necessary conversations
that would finally start happening.
That is the exact deliberate action Morgan is talking about.
It starts with facing reality.
It starts with facing the reality of your current culture,
not the fantasy version you put
on the About Us page of your website.
It reminds me of that one quote from the source material.
Morgan says, every organization already has a culture.
The only question is whether it's the one they want.
Exactly.
And that is the final thought I really want
everyone to sit with today.
You don't get to choose whether you have a culture or not.
You have one right now.
It is forming while we speak.
It is forming in your Slack channels.
It's forming in your Zoom chats,
in the hallway conversations,
and the way you structure your meeting agendas.
It is never neutral.
It is never, ever neutral.
Every single interaction is either building
the culture you want or it is destroying it.
It is compound interest,
and it's accumulating every second of every day.
That is powerful.
We are all architects of this stuff,
whether we realize it or not.
But let me add one more thought
for you to show on before we go.
Okay.
When you go out and ask those three people
that scary say-to-gap question this week,
pay close attention if they hesitate.
Oh, that's good.
What if the silence you hear when you ask that question
is actually the loudest part of your culture?
If they are too afraid to even answer you honestly,
that tells you everything you need to know
about your infrastructure.
That is a brilliant point.
If fear is your operational standard,
no strategy can save you.
So the real question isn't, do we have a culture?
The question is, is this the one we intended to build?
Right.
If the answer is no,
then you need to cancel the offsite,
stop printing the coffee mugs,
and start looking really closely at your daily habits.
Start looking at the speed limit you are actually driving.
Deliberate action.
That is the true takeaway here.
Thank you so much for walking us through this deep dive.
It has definitely made me rethink how I approach
my own team and maybe my own emails on the weekend.
My pleasure.
Just please, don't send the middle 11, 0 p.m.
I will do my absolute best.
And to you, the listener.
Good luck with those three questions this week.
It might be tough, but remember,
culture eats strategy for breakfast.
You might as well make sure it is a healthy breakfast.
Thanks for joining us on this deep dive.